So let's take a look at this task.
This is an old exercise.
You should also find
it in the task collection.
And this is a task like that:
We have class diagrams and object diagrams and want
to find out whether there is a fit in
each case.
This should happen in pairs for each of
the two class diagrams and each of the five
object diagrams.
To consider in each case:
Is this valid or not?
So does the object diagram
fit the class diagram or not?
We can go through that.
So let's look at the left
class diagram and the first object diagram.
What do we see there?
Specifically:
Does the object diagram
match the class diagram?
And one way to think about that
is always to go through the object diagram,
look at each object, and first look
at whether that object is justified in itself.
That is, whether it fits the class diagram in the sense
that the class of which it is supposed to be an
object exists at all.
You can see here, of course, that
I don't specify any attributes or methods.
So these are stylized classes and objects,
where it is only about the existence and
not about which properties
are additionally given by attributes.
So I would have to look now here only whether
A and C (thus the two classes, about which it
concerns here) exist at all.
Yes, they do exist in the class diagram.
So this object "a" or
the object "c" could already exist.
And then we have to see, if
all relations, which occur in the object diagram,
are justified by the class diagram.
And that none are missing.
So if we just take a look at
the "c" object, for example, and see what
relationships it has in the class
diagram, then it can have a relationship
to B objects in aggregation.
And now we can look:
There is no multiplicity at all.
That is, the default multiplicity
is to be used there.
And this is "0..*".
This means that the "c" may have
B partners, but it does not have to.
And in the concrete case
here it does not have them.
The "c" has no B-partners.
But this is not a big
deal, because it is not forced.
So this aggregation does not somehow lead
to the fact that something is missing.
And the "c" has no
other properties or relationship requirements.
From C there is no other association,
aggregation, composition somehow as a relation to other
classes.
And C doesn't inherit from anything either, so
it doesn't have any other requirements somehow that
it has to fulfill.
What about the "a" object?
That obviously belongs to this class A.
And there, of course, one can ask oneself, first
of all, whether all relations that are supposed to
exist from A are really given here.
There is especially this relation here,
but it has also "0..*" as multiplicities.
That means, "a" could have a
relation with itself or for example with
another A-object.
But it must not, because of this "0..*".
So for "a" and "c"
at least nothing is missing.
But what about this relation, which
is there in the object diagram?
It must be justified by something.
It is not enough to say that "c" and "a"
have nothing missing (so everything that "c" and "a" should
have, they have).
There must also be no relationship in the object
diagram that is not even provided for in the class
diagram.
And if we look:
There is no basis in the class diagram
for "c" to have a connection to "a" (that
is, a C object could have
a connection to an A object).
There is inheritance here, for example.
But that does not ensure that
C has any connection to A.
It says that B inherits from
A, not that A inherits from B.
Yes, if A inherited from B (if the inheritance
arrow were reversed here), then A would inherit from B
the relationship to C as well.
Then this link in the
object diagram would be quite justifiable.
But as the class diagram
1 looks, this is not so.
So here the answer would have to be:
It doesn't fit.
So (a) doesn't fit the first class diagram,
because this relationship between "a" and "c" from the
object diagram is not provided
in the class diagram at all.
Now we can ask ourselves:
What would it be like if we
had looked at the other class diagram?
And there is indeed the answer:
Yes that fits.
I'll just abbreviate that.
I have already talked
about this inheritance arrow.
That it goes in the wrong direction, so to
speak (for the fact that "a" could have a relationship
with "c").
Here the arrow is
exactly the other way round.
That is, there is no obvious relationship
between A and C in the class diagram.
But A inherits from B, and thus inherits
not only the attributes and methods, but also all
other relationships that B
has with any other classes.
So in particular, A inherits from
B also this relationship to C.
And that's why this
link is justified here.
And if we look at:
Are the multiplicities correct?
Yes.
"c" for example (it says so here)
must have a relation to at least
one B. That doesn't seem
to be the case at first.
Because here there are
no B-objects at all.
But every A-object is also
a B-object, because of this inheritance.
This "A inherits from B" means:
Every A-object is also a B-object.
That means, the requirement, that "c"
must be related to a B-object, is
fulfilled by this link here.
Because the "a", which is an A-object,
is also a B-object, because of inheritance.
And any other requirements that would
be violated here do not exist.
For example "a" does not have to have
a relationship to an A-object, since here nothing
is written, but then implicitly
"0..*" is written there as multiplicity.
So this self-relation on class level from A to
A, that does not necessarily have to be present
in an object diagram.
Because it is also possible that the
lower limit zero of the multiplicity is used
as incidence.
Okay, so that would explain (a)
for both the first and second class
diagrams.
Let's look at (b), again
for the first class diagram.
And look at whether all the
relationships that are here are justified.
And also whether none are missing.
So here:
Is there a relationship between
a B and a C object?
Yes, that fits.
That would correspond to this
aggregation in the class diagram.
There is the relationship between
a B and a D object.
And that fits as well.
That would correspond to this
relationship in the class diagram.
Okay, is there anything
that might be missing?
So what about B objects?
Do they need to
have any other relationships?
So there's aggregation to
C, that's satisfied anyway.
And it might be zero anyway, because
there are no multiplicities explicitly on it.
The same is true for this relation to D.
And the fact that B inherits from
A does not necessarily lead to further links.
Because A has this relation to A, but
just with these lower limits zero in each case.
So nothing follows from this that would
be somehow missing in the object diagram.
What about "c"?
There is nothing more
to be said about it.
So "c" can have relations with Bs.
In the concrete case it is
even so in the object diagram.
But there are also no multiplicities.
That means, zero would be
allowed as number by default anyway.
And what about the "d"?
There is indeed a requirement.
Namely this requirement here that each
D-object must be related to exactly
one B-object.
But that is the case here.
So it also fits.
Therefore (b) actually fits
to the first class diagram.
What about the second class diagram?
The fact that the inheritance arrow is now
reversed does not change anything in this specific
case.
This would simply mean that A could also
be here, but does not have to be.
We can also actually look at
a B-object concretely, so not an A-object,
which is automatically also a B-object.
And the other
requirements are also fulfilled.
So in particular, "b" is related to
at most one D to satisfy this.
And the C object is related to
at least one B object, so it also
satisfies this multiplicity here.
And the existing links here are
also covered by the class diagram.
So actually (b) fits both
the first and second class diagrams.
What about (c)?
Does that match the first class diagram?
We'll have to take a look at that:
Now we have an A-object here, so
the question arises, in how far this
changes something.
Just now we had this relationship
between "b" and "c" as a link.
That can't be the case here anymore.
Now there is an A here.
So this can only be
an expression of this relationship.
Let's see:
Does this justify that "b"
has a link navigable to "a"?
The "b", any B, is also an A.
And since As have such relations to
As, "b" may also have such relations.
So a B object (since it is also an
A object) can have a relationship to an A object.
That's exactly what we have here.
So this is a
manifestation of that relationship.
And these "0..*" or
"0..1" multiplicities are also
satisfied in the case here.
Okay, again this part, this is not at all different
from the case of (b), in the case of this
subtask.
That is, of course, that
corresponds to this relationship here.
So there are no other changes here.
The (c) fits the first class diagram.
Does (c) also fit
the second class diagram?
Let's take a look at that.
This will certainly raise the
question again, what justifies this link
here.
And we can't justify it now by
the fact that B inherits from A.
Now A inherits from B.
So with what right should a B-object
have a link to an A-object like here?
If we look at the class diagram, "b"
only has links to C and D objects.
A does inherit from B, but that means:
A can have all
the relationship that B has.
It does not mean B
can have relationships that A has.
So "b" may only have
relations to C and D objects.
To a D-object there
is such a relation here.
But this link here from a B object
to an A object, it's not justified or covered
or allowed for the second class diagram.
So (c) doesn't match
the second class diagram.
Okay, how about (d)?
Does (d) fit the first class diagram?
What's different about (d) now?
Now I have only A objects "a1",
"a2", "a3", all three from class A.
And here there is an A object
that has relationships to two other A objects.
So "a1" has relations to "a2" and "a3".
That would have to
be a manifestation of this.
And there we see, however,
that this is an illegal relationship.
In so far that they can't both exist.
Namely this one A-object has
relations concerning this association circled above
to two other A-objects.
But here it says as multiplicity at
this end, to which is navigated (that we
see indeed at this arrow here, that
this end should be obviously these two ends):
It says as multiplicity that this can
only be a relation to at most
one A-object.
That is:
What we see down here
in the object diagram is wrong.
It violates that multiplicity here.
Okay, how about the second class diagram?
Maybe it fits there.
Does (d) fit the second class diagram?
And the answer is:
So B, C, D objects don't exist at all.
So there can't be
any requirements or prohibitions there.
We just have to look at A.
The fact that A inherits from
B doesn't matter in this case.
Because only possible relations to C
and D would result from it.
But these are not obligatory in each
case, because here just "0..1" and implicitly
"0..*".
So A inherits these two relations from
B, but no obligations result from it,
only possibilities.
And how is it with
these two relations and this relation?
These two links are covered
by that relationship up there.
Because it says:
An A-object can be related (in the
end it says "0..*") with any number
of other A-objects.
So for example also with two.
And vice versa, so to say
in backward direction, in this direction:
"a2" and "a3" may each be related
to "0..*" A-objects in this direction.
In this multiplicity, of course, having
a partner here falls into this
interval.
So (d) fits the second class diagram,
although it had not fit the first.
Okay, and then finally
the questions for (e).
So how about for (e)?
Does (e) fit the first class diagram?
Now the As have disappeared.
So there are no A objects.
There is a B object, which is also
an A object because of the inheritance here.
So we have to look at
what the requirements are because of that.
But because the relation here above is
so liberal (always also allowed by the multiplicities
that zero is present as the number
of counterparts), there are no further obligations
for the B-object.
So that's harmless there.
And what about the C and D relations?
So "b" may be related
to any number of D-objects.
That would be these two in this case.
It does not have to be related
to C-objects, because here the multiplicity is
implicitly "0..*".
And every D-object must be related to
exactly one B-object, because of this specification here.
But that is also the case here.
Yes, each D-object is
related to exactly one B-object.
That these two D-objects are both
related to the same B-object is not
a big deal.
Because that is allowed from the B point of
view to be related to any number of D objects.
So (e) fits the first class diagram.
And then as a final question, I
wonder if (e) also fits the second class
diagram here.
And how is that?
There is a problem
with this multiplicity here.
Because each B-object may only be
related to at most one D-object.
But here there are
these two counterparts for "b".
So these two links can
only be manifestations of this relation.
Because there are no other relations between
B and D, not even by inheritance somehow.
And then this multiplicity, which
is required here, is violated.
The "b" is allowed to have no D-partner at all,
or to have one D-partner, but not more than one.
Each b object is allowed to have at most
one D object as a counterpart along a link
for that association.
And that is apparently violated here.
So (e) does not
match the second class diagram.
With this, we have discussed all cases.